<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ParsedDocxDocument xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
  <WerkId>0009</WerkId>
  <WerkTitel>Historiarum libri quinque</WerkTitel>
  <Alternativtitel>
    <Titel>Historiarum libri quinque ab anno incarnationis 900 usque ad a. 1044</Titel>
    <Titel>Geschichte der Jahre 900 bis 1044 in fünf Büchern</Titel>
  </Alternativtitel>
  <Autoren>
    <Autor>Rodulf der Kahle</Autor>
    <Autor>Rodulfus Glaber</Autor>
  </Autoren>
  <LebensdatenVerfasser>980/985-1047</LebensdatenVerfasser>
  <Abfassungszeitraum>1031-1047</Abfassungszeitraum>
  <Abfassungsort>Cluny; Auxerre</Abfassungsort>
  <Regionen>
    <Region>West- und Mitteleuropa – Westfrankenreich</Region>
  </Regionen>
  <Editionshinweise>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque, ed. John France (Oxford Medieval Texts), Oxford 1989, S. 2-253.</Editionshinweise>
  <Werkinformation>Die Historiarum libri quinque wurde von Rodulfus Glaber (Rodulf der Kahle) ab ca. 1030 bis ca. 1044 verfasst und Abt Odilo von Cluny gewidmet. Der Verfasser berichtet hier in fünf Büchern über die Jahre 900 bis 1044, mit einem Schwerpunkt auf dem Jahrhundertwechsel. Rodulfus erwähnt Mohammed hier erstmals für ein nordeuropäisches Werk.
Vgl. auch mit Hinweisen für weiterführende Literatur Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque ab anno incarnationis 900 usque ad a. 1044, in: Repertorium ‚Geschichtsquellen des deutschen Mittelalters‘ [http://www.geschichtsquellen.de/repOpus_04108.html, 2016-08-11]; Michael Frassetto, Art. Rodulf Glaber, in: Encyclopedia of the Medieval Chronicle 2 (2010), S. 1289; Jan Prelog, Art. Raoul Glaber, in: Lexikon des Mittelalters 7, Sp. 933 [Brepolis Medieval Encyclopaedias – Lexikon des Mittelalters Online, 2016-08-11].
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</Werkinformation>
  <Quellen>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0001</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, IV, 8, ed. France 1989, S. 18.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>vor 973</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Sarazenen aus Afrika besetzen während der Herrschaft Kaiser Ottos I. (936-973) Gebiete in den Alpen und verwüsten die Region.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Huius [Otto I.] quoque imperii tempore egressi audacter Sarraceni ab Affricanis [Afrika] partibus occupauere tutiora Alpium [Alpen] montium loca, ibique aliquandiu morantes, uastando regionem in gyro diuerso raptu tempus expleuerunt.</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>During his [Otto I.] reign the Saracens boldly sallied out from Africa [Afrika] and seized many strong places in the Alps [Alpen]; and there they stayed for a while, passing the time by wasting the region round about with raids of various kinds.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, IV, 8, ed. France 1989, S. 19.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="936-973" From="936-01-01" To="973-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="930-940" From="930-01-01" To="940-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="940-950" From="940-01-01" To="950-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="950-960" From="950-01-01" To="960-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="960-970" From="960-01-01" To="970-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="970-980" From="970-01-01" To="980-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>Afrika</Ort>
        <Ort>Ostfrankenreich (Deutschland, Schweiz, Österreich)</Ort>
        <Ort>Alpen</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>n</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Invasion</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Plünderung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Zerstörung</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Africa</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Afrika</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Affricanus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Afrikaner</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>-</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="d0af59f7-9a56-4788-a442-b04a20f68eb8" Type="Person">
          <Name>Otto I.</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="ba80122a-4252-4873-8bf3-70e81768f5cb" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Afrika</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="d59a2dcd-2976-447a-a7c6-a1356b02e43d" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Alpen</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0002</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, IV, 9, ed. France 1989, S. 18-22.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>vor 973</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Abt Maiolus von Cluny wird [972/973] zusammen mit seinen Begleitern von Sarazenen von La Garde-Freinet gefangen genommen und gegen ein Lösegeld freigegeben. Daraufhin werden die Sarazenen durch ein Heeresaufgebot Graf Wilhelms von Arles erfolgreich vertrieben.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Contigit ergo eodem tempore ut beatus pater Maiolus [Abt Maiolus von Cluny], ab Italia [Italien] rediens, in artissimis Alpium [Alpen] eosdem Sarracenos obuiaret. […] Dispertitis quoque inter se omnibus que illius fuerant, interrogauerunt eum si tante ei essent in patria facultates rerum, quibus uidelicet se suosque ualeret redimere de manibus illorum. Tunc uir Dei, ut erat totius affabilitatis dignitate precipuus, respondit se in hoc mundo nil proprium possidere, nec peculiaris rei se fieri possessorem uelle, sua tamen ditione non negans plures teneri qui amplorum fundorum et pecuniarum domini haberentur. Quibus auditis ipsimet hortabantur illum ut unum e suis mitteret, qui sue suorumque redemptionis pretium illis deferret. […] Misit quoque uir sanctus per unum de suis ad monasterium scilicet cui preerat Cluniacense [Cluny] perparuam epistulam ita se habentem: ‚Dominis et fratribus Cluniensibus, frater Maiolus miser et captus. Torrentes Belial circumdederunt me, praeoccupauerunt me laquei mortis. Nunc uero si placet pro me et his qui mecum capti tenentur redemptionem mittite.‘ […] Tandem uero quidam de fratribus illuc expeditius remeantes, data eisdem Sarracenis presignata pecunia, patrem cum uiris qui cum eo capti fuerant in patriam reduxerunt. Ipsi denique Sarraceni paulo post in loco qui Fraxinetus [La Garde-Freinet] dicitur circumacti ab exercitu Wilelmi Arelatensis ducis [Graf Wilhelm von Arles], omnesque in breui perierunt, ut ne unus quidem redirect in patriam.</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>It was during this time that the holy father Mayol [Abt Maiolus von Cluny], returning from Italy [Italien], encounteres these Saracens in the narrow passes of the Alps [Alpen]. […] When the Saracens had shared out all his belonging among themselves, they asked if Mayol had sufficient resources in his own country to ransom himself and his people from their hands. Then the man of God, ever dignified and courtenous, replied that in this world he possessed nothing of his own, and had no desire to do so, but he did not deny that he held jurisdiction over many men who had great estates and wealth. Then the Saracens urged him to send one of his people to bring back ransom money for himself and his companions. […] The holy man sent one of his companions to his monastery of Cluny [Cluny] with a brief letter, which read: “Brother Mayol, a captive and in misery, sends greetings to his lords and brethren, the monk of Cluny. The hordes of Belial have encircled me, the snares of death have seized me. Please send a ransom for me and those held captive with me.” […] At last some of the brethren returned in haste, gave the Saracens the agreed ransom, and took home the holy father and all those who had been held captive with him. As for the Saracens, they were eventually surrounded a little later by the army of William, count of Arles [Graf Wilhelm von Arles], in the place called La Garde-Freinet [La Garde-Freinet], and in a short space all perished, so that not one returned to his country.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, IV, 9, ed. France 1989, S.19-23.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="972/973" From="972-01-01" To="972-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="972/973" From="973-01-01" To="973-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="970-980" From="970-01-01" To="980-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>Ostfrankenreich (Deutschland, Schweiz, Österreich)</Ort>
        <Ort>Alpen</Ort>
        <Ort>Westfrankenreich (Frankreich)</Ort>
        <Ort>La Garde-Freinet</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>aK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>j</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Gefangennahme</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Kampfhandlung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Vertreibung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Freilassung</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Fraxinetum</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>La Garde-Freinet</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>Vgl. zum Heeresaufgebot des Grafen Wilhelm von Arles Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, IV, 9, ed. France, S. 23, Anm. 2.
Die Entführung des Maiolus fand laut Scott G. Bruce, Cluny and the Muslims of La Garde-Freinet. Hagiography and the problem of Islam in Medieval Europe, Ithaca – London 2015, S. 33 in der Nacht vom 21. auf den 22. Juli 972 statt. Bruce bezieht sich bei der Datierung auf Paul-Antonin Amargier, La capture de saint Maieul de Cluny et l’expulsion des Sarrasins de Provnece, Revue bénédictine 73 (1963), S. 316-323, S. 319. Die Vertreibung der Sarazenen durch Christen wird unmittelbar nach der Befreiung des Maiolus aus der Gefangenschaft angesetzt und mit einem Vorgehen Wilhelms II. von Arles, Gf. der Provence, verbunden. Die Datierung der hier geschilderten Ereignisse ist allerdings nicht vollkommen sicher. So werden in Anlehnung an Jean-Pierre Poly zumeist die Jahre 972/973 angenommen. Mit Sicherheit lässt sich über die Vertreibung der Sarazenen aus La Garde-Freinet allerdings nur sagen, dass diese bis zu Beginn der 980er Jahre geschehen ist, vgl. hierzu Jean-Pierre Poly, La Provence et la Société féodale (879-1166). Contributions à l’étude des structures dites féodales dans le Midi, Paris 1976, S. 28f.; Neithard Bulst, Maiolus, in: Lexikon des Mittelalters 6, Sp. 145-146 [Brepolis Medieval Encyclopaedias – Lexikon des Mittelalters Online, 2017-08-31]. Daneben wird auch die These vertreten, dass die Vertreibung der Sarazenen zu Beginn der 980er Jahre erfolgte, vgl. Georges de Manteyer, La Marche de Provence jusqu’aux partages et l’Évêché d’Avignon jusqu’a la commune, in: Positions des thèses soutenues par les élèves de la promotion de … pour obtenir le diplôme d’archiviste-paléographe (1897), S. 56f.; René Poupardin, Le royaume de Bourgogne (888-1038). Etudes sur les origines du royaume d’Arles (Bibliothèque de l’Ecole des Hautes Etudes 4. Section Sciences Historiques et Philologiques 163), Paris 1907, S. 97.
Vgl. hierzu auch die Berichte in den Maiolus-Viten des Odilo, des Syrus und des Nagold, [0063]-[0001], [0064-0001] und [0066]-[0002].</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="35c14758-ba4e-45e6-b364-ecd12c75c765" Type="Person">
          <Name>Abt Maiolus von Cluny</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="650b43d3-3751-4410-a116-9bafde2cfb82" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Italien</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="d59a2dcd-2976-447a-a7c6-a1356b02e43d" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Alpen</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="4011fdf6-1feb-4805-b7a9-56e05c2b9129" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Cluny</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="dd931c19-4b3f-4431-9fca-62eeb12226e3" Type="Ort">
          <Name>La Garde-Freinet</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="32f40d9e-9e0c-4f82-a055-fb282922fe11" Type="Person">
          <Name>Graf Wilhelm von Arles</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0003</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, V, 17, ed. France 1989, S. 32.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>um 900</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Sarazenen aus Spanien dringen unter der Führung ihres Herrschers [Abd ar-Rahman III.] um 900 [929-961] nach Italien ein und plündern die Region um Benevent. Anschließend ziehen sie weiter nach Afrika und unternehmen bis zur Herrschaft des Kalifen Abu Amir al-Mansūr [978-1002] weiterhin Beutezüge nach Italien.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Denique circa nongentesimum Verbi incarnati annum, egressus ab Hispania [Spanien] rex Sarracenorum Algalif [Kalif Abd ar-Rahman III.], ueniensque cum exercitu maximo in Italiam [Italien], scilicet traditurus humanas res cum suis in predam tum gladio atque incendio demoliendas. Qui dum uenisset, depopulans totam regionem usque Beneuentum [Benevent] progressus est. Ex aliquibus tamen ciuitatibus Italiae primates collecto agmine nisi sunt aduersus predictum Algalif inire pugnam. Sed cum se cernerent exercitu nimium impares, ut sepius mos est istis modernis Italicis, fuge potius quam bellum petiere presidium. Interea reuersi cum suo principe ad Affricam [Afrika] Sarraceni, ab illo tempore non destiterunt impugnare regionem Italie [Italien], quamuis plurimis fuissent preliis lacessiti tam ab imperatoribus quam a partie ducibus ac marchionibus, usque ad Almuzor [Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr] illorum principem et predictum Henricum Romanorum imperatorem [Heinrich II.].</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>About the year 900 of the Incarnate World, Algalif king of the Saracens [Kalif Abd ar-Rahman III.] left Spain [Spanien] and came with a great army into Italy [Italien] intent to handing over men’s property to be plundered by his men or put to the sword and burned. Once arrived he ravaged the entire region right up to Benevento [Benevent]. The princes of Italy gathered together an army drawn from some cities, intending to attack Algalif, but when they recognized the inadequacy of their force, they sought safety in flight rather than battle, as is so often the way with these modern Italians. In the meantime the Saracens returned to Africa [Afrika] with their prince, and, from then until the time of al-Mansūr [Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr] their ruler and Henry emperor of the Romans [Heinrich II.], they never stopped attacking Italy [Italien], despite the many wars waged against them both by the emperors and by the dukes and marquesses of that land.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, V, 17, ed. France 1989, S. 33.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="929-961" From="929-01-01" To="961-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="978-1002" From="978-01-01" To="1002-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="920-930" From="920-01-01" To="930-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="930-940" From="930-01-01" To="940-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="940-950" From="940-01-01" To="950-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="950-960" From="950-01-01" To="960-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="960-970" From="960-01-01" To="970-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="970-980" From="970-01-01" To="980-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="980-990" From="980-01-01" To="990-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="990-1000" From="990-01-01" To="1000-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1000-1010" From="1000-01-01" To="1010-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>Afrika</Ort>
        <Ort>Iberische Halbinsel (Spanien, Portugal)</Ort>
        <Ort>Italien</Ort>
        <Ort>Benevent</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>n</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Überfall</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Plünderung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Kampfhandlung</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Africa</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Affrica</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Afrika</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Amir</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Emir</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Hispania</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Spanien</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>Der in der Quelle verwendete Begriff ‚Algalif‘ kann entweder allgemein für ‚al-halifa‘ (Kalif) stehen oder für die Dynastie der Aghlabiden, welche 827-900 Sizilien beherrschten, vgl. hierzu Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, V, 17, ed. France, S. 32, Anm. 2. Möglicherweise steht ‚Algalif‘ für Abd ar-Rahman III., der in den Jahren 929-961 als erster Kalif von Cordoba regierte. Auf diese Weise erscheint die unpräzise Datierung der Quelle für den Einfall in Italien [um 900] gewissermaßen schlüssig. Gesichert ist diese Annahme aber nicht. Zu den Herrschaftsjahren des Kalifen Abu Amir al-Mansūr vgl. ebd., S. 33, Anm. 3.</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="1b3bc365-6179-45d1-b0bd-21aab4abd3e3" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Spanien</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="749b489a-c31c-4146-b9b9-8f3195eb62ec" Type="Person">
          <Name>Kalif Abd ar-Rahman III.</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="650b43d3-3751-4410-a116-9bafde2cfb82" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Italien</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="399563a8-1c2d-4669-867f-f8c29c88ceb9" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Benevent</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="ba80122a-4252-4873-8bf3-70e81768f5cb" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Afrika</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="33b5547b-c366-4428-b5b0-6c751d443199" Type="Person">
          <Name>Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="bcfcec49-0687-4e38-8693-d18c402879c5" Type="Person">
          <Name>Heinrich II.</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0004</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque II, IX, 18, ed. France 1989, S. 82.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>um 1003/1004</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Sarazenen aus Afrika besetzen um 1003/1004 [1000-1002] unter Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr große Teile Spaniens und töten dabei viele Christen. Sancho III. der Große [s. Anm.] stellt sich ihnen erfolgreich entgegen. Beide Seiten haben schwere Verluste hinzunehmen.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Subsequente namque tempore gens Sarracenorum cum rege suo, Almuzor nomine [Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr], egressa est ex Africanis [Afrika] partibus, ocupans pene uniuersam Hispanie [Spanien] regionem usque in australes Galliarum [Gallien] fines, plurimasque Christianorum dedere strages. Sed licet inpar exercitu, sepius tamen iniit cum eis prelia Willelmus dux Nauarrie, cognomento Sanctus [Sancho III. der Große?, s. Anm.]. Tunc etiam ob exercitus raritatem conpulsi sunt regionis illius monachi sumere arma bellica. Cese denique grauiter utreque partes; tandem concessa Christianis uictoria, post grande suorum dispendium, qui superfuere Sarracenorum ad Africam [Afrika] fecere confugium. Sed et in illis diutinis conflictibus preliorum constat Christianorum religiosos plures ocubuisse, qui potius ob fraterne caritatis amorem cupierant decertare quam propter aliquam gloriolam laudis ponpatice.</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>Shortly afterwards the Saracens, with their king al-Mansūr [Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr], surged forth from Africa [Afrika] and seized almost all Spain [Spanien] as far as the southern boundaries of Gaul [Gallien], massacring many Christians. William duke of Navarre, called Sancho [Sancho III. der Große?, s. Anm.], did not hesitate to challenge him frequently in battle, although his army was nowhere near as big. Indeed the army was so small that the monks of that area were compelled to take up arms. After great losses on both sides victory went to Christians, while the surviving Saracens, after heavy casualities, retreated to Africa [Afrika]. During these long wars many religious in the Christian armies were killed; they had longed to fight for love of their brothers, not for any vain glory of renown and pomp.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque II, IX, 18, ed. France 1989, S. 83.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="1000-1002" From="1000-01-01" To="1002-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1000-1010" From="1000-01-01" To="1010-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>Afrika</Ort>
        <Ort>Iberische Halbinsel (Spanien, Portugal)</Ort>
        <Ort>Westfrankenreich (Frankreich)</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>aK</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>j</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Invasion</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Kampfhandlung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Überfall</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Tod</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Vertreibung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Sieg</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Zerstörung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Schutzmaßnahme</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Africa</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Afrika</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Africanus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Afrikanisch</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Hispania</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Spanien</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>Es ist denkbar, dass der Historiograph Sancho III. den Großen und Graf Wilhelm-Sancho von der Gascogne vertauschte und aufgrund dessen von Willelmus dux Nauarrie, cognomento Sanctus berichtet, vgl. hierzu Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque II, IX, 18, ed. France, S. 82, Anm. 2.</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="33b5547b-c366-4428-b5b0-6c751d443199" Type="Person">
          <Name>Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="ba80122a-4252-4873-8bf3-70e81768f5cb" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Afrika</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="1b3bc365-6179-45d1-b0bd-21aab4abd3e3" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Spanien</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="3e9ca6a5-4860-45ff-be26-49bb12879dfe" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Gallien</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="26f9ea12-4bd4-4d9e-b573-35a9037c4000" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>Sancho III. der Große?, s. Anm.</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0005</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque II, IX, 19, ed. France 1989, S. 82ff.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>um 1003/1004</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Der Mönch Wulferius aus dem Kloster Réome [heutiges Kloster Moutiers-Saint-Jean am Fluss Réome] hat um 1003/1004 [Mai/Juni um 1000-1002] eine Vision weiß gekleideter Männer, die ehrenvoll im Kampf gegen Sarazenen gefallen sind.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Erat quippe eo tempore frater quidam, Vulferius [Wulferius] nomine, dulcis admodum moribus et conuersatione, in monasterio cognomento Reomagensse [Réome], quod est situm in pago Tarnoderensse [Tonnerre], cui etiam aparuit die quadam dominica uisio satis credulitati commoda. Nam dum post expletionem matutinalium laudum in supradicto oraturus quieuisset monasterio, fratribus ceteris inde aliquantulum ad pausam redeuntibus, subito repletus est totius eiusdem ecclesie ambitus, uiris scilicet uestibus albis indutis ac purpureis stolis insignitis, […]. Interim uero percunctatus est supradictus frater qui aut unde essent, pro quaue causa illuc deuenissent. Cui satis leuiter tale dederunt responsum: ‚Professionem’ inquiunt ‚Christianitatis gestamus, sed ob tutelam partie catholiceque plebis defensionem gladius nos in bello Sarracenorum separauit ab humanorum corporum habitatione. Idcirco nos omnes pariter diuina uocatio nunc transfert in sortem beatorum; sed ideo per hanc prouinciam nobis contigit habere transitum quoniam plures ex hac regione infra breue temporis spacium nostro sunt addendi collegio.‘ […] Intellexit quoque idem frater se in breui spatio exiturum a seculo, quod etiam sic contigit fieri.</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>At that time there was a monk called Wulferius, a man of impeccable life and converse, who lived in the monastery of Réome [Réome] in the country of Tonnerre [Tonnerre]; one Sunday he had a vision which is well worthy of belief. It so happened that after matins he remained behind to pray in the church, while the other brothers had gone back to rest awhile. Suddenly the whole church was filled with men dressed in white robes and wearing purple stoles; […] In the meantime brother Wulferius asked them who they were, whence they had come, and why to that place. They replied with light hearts, saying: “We are all men of Christian profession, but while we were fighting for the defence of our country and the Christian people against the Saracens, the sword severed us from this earthly flesh. Because of this divine Providence is now taking us all into the lot of the blessed; it had befallen us to pass through this province because many from here must shortly be added to our number.” […] Wulferius understood by this that he was to die soon, and so it fell out.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque II, IX, 19, ed. France 1989, S. 83ff.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="Mai/Juni um 1000-1002" From="995-01-01" To="1002-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="990-1000" From="990-01-01" To="1000-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1000-1010" From="1000-01-01" To="1010-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>Westfrankenreich (Frankreich)</Ort>
        <Ort>Réome</Ort>
        <Ort>Tonnerre</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>aK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>n</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Kampfhandlung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Vorzeichen</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>Zur Bestimmung der Jahresangaben vgl. Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque II, IX, 18, ed. France, S. 85.</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="b18135d4-25d6-4ca5-ba0f-6b64e8632775" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>Wulferius</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="cc54948a-4f8d-439c-846e-20776486046c" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>Réome</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="63b734bb-7044-4a42-aa58-54c191940ce9" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Tonnerre</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0006</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque III, VII, 24, ed. France 1989, S. 132ff.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>1009</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Im Auftrag des Kalifen Al-Hākim bi-Amr-Allāh aus Ägypten wird 1009 [1010] durch eine List der Juden die Grabeskirche von Jerusalem sowie die Kirche des Hl. Märtyrers Georg in Ramla zerstört, welche bisher von Sarazenen aus Furcht unangetastet geblieben ist.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Eo quoque in tempore, id est anno nono post prefatum millesimum, ecclesia, que apud Hierosolimam [Jerusalem] sepulchrum continebat Domini ac Saluatoris nostri, euersa est funditus iussu principis Babilonis [Kalif Al-Hākim bi-Amr-Allāh]. […] Hi [Iudaei gens] denique nequam consilio inito corruperunt quendam, data pecunia, uidelicet girouagum sub peregrino habitu, nomine Rotbertum [Rotbert], fugitiuum utique seruum beate Marie Melerensis [Moutiers-Sainte-Marie] cenobii. Quem accipientes caute miserunt ad principem Babilonis cum Hebraicis caracteribus scriptis epistolis, […]. Qui egressus detulit litteras predicto principi refertas dolo et nequitia, et quoniam nisi celerius domum Christianorum uenerabilem subuerteret, sciret se in proximum Christianis regnum illius occupantibus omni penitus dignitate carere. His uero princeps auditis, protinus furore arreptus, misit Hierosolimam [Jerusalem] de suis qui predictum funditus subuerterent templum. […] Tunc etiam beati martyris Georgii ecclesiam in Ramulo [Ramla] partier subuerterunt, cuius olim uirtus Sarracenorum nimium gentem terruerat; fertur enim crebro illuc eos ingredi cupientes raptum cecitatem pertulisse.</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>In the same ninth year after the millennium the church at Jerusalem [Jerusalem], which contained the Sepulchre of Our Lord and Saviour, was destroyed at the command of the Prince of Cairo [Kalif Al-Hākim bi-Amr-Allāh]. […] They [the Jews] conceived a dastardly plot: they bribed one Robert, a fugitive serf from the house of Moutiers-Sainte-Marie, who was no more than a vagabond masquerading as a pilgrim. With infinite precaution they sent him to the prince of Cairo with letters written in the Hebrew alphabet; […] The fellow set off and delivered these letters, which were full of evil and lies: they alleged that if he did not quickly destroy the venerable Church of the Christians, then they would soon occupy his whole realm, depriving him of all his power. When the prince heard this he was transported with rage, and he sent some of his servants to Jerusalem [Jerusalem] to destroy the church. […] Then they also destroyed the church of the holy martyr George of Ramla [Ramla], although previously his power had always terrified the Saracens, for it is said that he often struck blind those who invaded his church in search of plunder.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque III, VII, 24, ed. France 1989, S. 133ff.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="1010" From="1010-01-01" To="1010-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1000-1010" From="1000-01-01" To="1010-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>Israel</Ort>
        <Ort>Jerusalem</Ort>
        <Ort>Ramla</Ort>
        <Ort>Westfrankenreich (Frankreich)</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>aK</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>n</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Überfall</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Zerstörung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Hinterhalt/-list</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Hl. Stätte</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Heiligenschändung</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Babilonia</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Babylon</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Hierosolyma</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Hierosolima</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Jerusalem</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>-</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="107ceb7a-8e2a-4ce7-847a-8ada274b5ed5" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Jerusalem</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="50ac7d6c-1fb5-47fa-b6c8-8f0fa8063517" Type="Person">
          <Name>Kalif Al-Hākim bi-Amr-Allāh</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="465beb26-0c99-4ca2-9fc0-a075484914a2" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>Iudaei gens</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="14c1d945-37c2-4d2c-9dcd-ec9065573d1d" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>Rotbert</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="d49f7d0d-e077-4263-9a05-e9eaddeab212" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>Moutiers-Sainte-Marie</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="84b1ed32-c42c-4024-8e98-232d0cd52562" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Ramla</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="79564286-81f9-46d9-b080-901a7570d2cb" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>the Jews</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0007</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque IV, VI, 19, ed. France 1989, S. 202.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>Mitte des 11. Jahrhunderts</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Bischof Ulrich von Orléans berichtet [1032-1035] über ein Wunder, welches sich an Ostern ereignet haben soll und von einem Sarazenen handelt, der besessen von einem Dämon vor den Augen anderer Sarazenen und Christen an seinen Qualen gestorben sei.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Eodem quippe tempore Odolricus [Bf. Ulrich von Orléans], Aurelianorum presul, illuc pergens, quid uiderit nobisque narrauerit non pretermittendum uidetur miraculum. Die igitur magni illius sabbati quo ignis mirabili Dei potentia ueniens ab uniuerso populo prestolatur, ibi cum ceteris isdem presul adstabat. Iamque dies ipsa in uesperum transiens, repente penes horam qua sperabatur ignis affuturus, unus Sarracenorum scurra impudentissimus, ex plurima illorum multitudine que annuatim semper una cum Christianis adesse solet, exclamauit, ut Christianis mos est, cum primum uidetur: ‘Aios Kyrrieleison!’ Cauillanter cachinnum emisit, extensaque manu arripuit cereum de manu cuiusdam Christiani, aufugere temptans. Qui ilico arreptus a demonio turpiter nimium uexari cepit. Quem prosequens Christianus cereum abstulit. Ille uero tortus acerrime, protinus inter Sarracenorum manus exspirauit. Quod factum omnibus in commune terrorem immisit, Christicolis tamen gaudium et exultationem prebuit.</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>At the same time Ulric bishop of Orléans [Bf. Ulrich von Orléans] undertook this journey; and he told us about a miracle which should not be passed over. On the day of the great Sabbath when all the people gathered together to await the Holy Fire wondrously lit by the power of God, he was amongst them. Evening was drawing in when suddenly, just at the time when the fire was to appear, a Saracen, truly an imprudent jester, one of the crowd of that race which every year gathers and mixes with the Christians, cried out in the manner of the Christians when the fire is first seen: ‘Aios Kyrie Eleison [Holy Lord, have mercy upon us].’ Then, laughing aloud mockingly he reached out and snatched a candle from the hand of one of the Christians and made to flee. But he was seized by a demon who much troubled him. The Christians followed him and took back his candle. The fellow at once died in agony in the hands of the other Saracens. This event terrified all the Saracens alike, but brought joy and exaltation to the Christians.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque IV, VI, 19, ed. 1989, S. 203.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="1032-1035" From="1032-01-01" To="1035-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>-</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aK</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sI</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>j</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Sieg</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Vorzeichen</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Gottesurteil</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>Die Datierung ergibt sich aus der Amtszeit des Bischofs von Orléans, vgl. Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque IV, V, 19, ed. France, S. 202, Anm. 1.</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="ab18e9e3-0822-4854-ab7c-2bc99fb9efb7" Type="Person">
          <Name>Bf. Ulrich von Orléans</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="d5798ef1-ad05-4734-8d27-22a23ce8cf00" Type="Anmerkung">
          <Name>Holy Lord, have mercy upon us</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
    <Quelle>
      <QuellenId>0008</QuellenId>
      <Zitation>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque IV, VII, 22, ed. France 1989, S. 206.</Zitation>
      <ZeitangabeQuelle>Mitte des 11. Jahrhunderts</ZeitangabeQuelle>
      <Inhaltsangabe>Ein christliches Heer kann [1002] die aus Afrika kommenden Sarazenen vernichtend schlagen und den Kalifen Abu Amir al-Mansūr töten.</Inhaltsangabe>
      <VolltextOriginalsprache>Sub hisdem uero temporibus consurgens rediuiua Sarracenorum in Affrice [Afrika] partibus aduersus Christianorum populum perfidia, persequendo eos terra marique quosquos repperire poterant, quosdam excoriabant uiuos, alios trucidabant; et cum iam diu multumque inter utrosque debacatum plurima cede fuisset, pluresque strages ab utrisque partibus date, contigit ut ex deliberatione partis utriusque in comminus illorum acies pugnature deuenirent. Illi presumentes confidebant in rabida feritate immense sue multitudinis, uictores sese fore existimabant, nostri uero, licet admodum pauci numero, Dei omnipotentis auxilium inuocantes, per interuentum genitricis ipsius Marie sanctique apostolorum principis Petri omniumque sanctorum sperabant de illis fiducialiter obtinere triumphum, […]. Christiani tamen omnino inlesi uictores apparebant; ad ultimum quoque tantus horroris tremor inuasit Sarracenorum exercitum ut, ueluti pugne obliti, fugam arripere temptantes, quamuis nequicquam: propriis irretiti iaculis, immo uirtute Dei stupentes heserunt, Christianorum uero quantus erat cuneus diuino fortificatus auxilio tanta eosdem cede prostrauit ut ex innumerabili multitudine illorum uix pauci euaderent. Motget nempe princeps illorum, qui quasi Moyses [Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr] ita confuse nominator, illo prelio dicitur defuisse.</VolltextOriginalsprache>
      <VolltextUebersetzung>At this time the treachery of the Saracens of Africa [Afrika] against the Christians revived, and they attacked by land and sea, taking all they could find; some they flayed alive, others they butchered. The maniac killing on both sides went on for a long time, and each side suffered terrible destruction, so that in the end they both agreed to bring their armies to battle at the earliest possible moment. The arrogant enemy, trusting in the raging ferocity of their enormous host, believed victory was theirs, but our people, though very few in number, invoked the aid of God Almighty through the intercession of His Mother Mary, the holy Peter, Prince of the Apostles, and all the saints, and so they confidently looked forward to a triumph. […] The Christians suffered no losses and were clearly victorious; finally a tremor ran through the Saracen army and the enemy, as if unmindful of the fight, sought to flee, but in vain; for they were entangled in their own spears – or rather, by the might of God – and were struck there dumbfounded. The army of God, made irresistible by divine aid, killed so many of them that only a handful of that unnumbered multitude survived. It is said that Mujāhid [Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr] their prince, whose name is the name as Moses, but corrupted, died in the battle.</VolltextUebersetzung>
      <ZitationUebersetzung>Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque IV, VII, 22, ed. France 1989, S. 207.</ZitationUebersetzung>
      <ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
        <Datum Text="1002" From="1002-01-01" To="1002-12-31" />
      </ZeitangabeWissenschaft>
      <Berichtszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1000-1010" From="1000-01-01" To="1010-12-31" />
      </Berichtszeitraum>
      <Abfassungszeitraum>
        <Datum Text="1030-1040" From="1030-01-01" To="1040-12-31" />
        <Datum Text="1040-1050" From="1040-01-01" To="1050-12-31" />
      </Abfassungszeitraum>
      <GeographischesStichwort>
        <Ort>Afrika</Ort>
      </GeographischesStichwort>
      <Beteiligte>
        <Beteiligter>aK</Beteiligter>
        <Beteiligter>sK</Beteiligter>
      </Beteiligte>
      <Interaktion>j</Interaktion>
      <Auffaelligkeiten>
        <Schlagwort>Invasion</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Kampfhandlung</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Sieg</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Tod</Schlagwort>
        <Schlagwort>Gottesurteil</Schlagwort>
      </Auffaelligkeiten>
      <Suchbegriffe>
        <Suchwort>Africa</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Affrica</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Afrika</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Saracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarracenus</Suchwort>
        <Suchwort>Sarazene</Suchwort>
      </Suchbegriffe>
      <Anmerkungen>Die Datierung ergibt sich aus dem Todesjahr des Kalifen Abu Amir al-Mansūr, vgl. Rodulfus Glaber, Historiarum libri quinque I, V, 17, ed. France, S. 33, Anm. 3.</Anmerkungen>
      <Entitaeten>
        <Entitaet Id="ba80122a-4252-4873-8bf3-70e81768f5cb" Type="Ort">
          <Name>Afrika</Name>
        </Entitaet>
        <Entitaet Id="33b5547b-c366-4428-b5b0-6c751d443199" Type="Person">
          <Name>Kalif Abu Amir al-Mansūr</Name>
        </Entitaet>
      </Entitaeten>
    </Quelle>
  </Quellen>
</ParsedDocxDocument>